Inventory of the Papers of Judge John W. Bissell, 1983-2005
University of Virginia, Arthur J. Morris Law Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
Inventory of the Papers of Judge John W. Bissell 1983-2005
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
MSS 05-1
This collection contains 80 boxes of files (27 linear feet).
The Papers of Judge John W. Bissell document his service on the U.S. District Court for the district of New Jersey from 1983-2005. The collection consists mainly of unpublished opinions, with a few published opinions and articles of correspondence selected for preservation by Judge Bissell.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
[Written by Audrey Golden, based on her own research and an interview with Judge Bissell that she conducted in July 2010.]
Retired Judge John Winslow Bissell presided over the United States District Court for the District of New Jersey from 1982-2005 after being nominated by then-President Reagan, and he served as Chief Judge from 2001 until the end of his tenure. Prior to serving as a federal judge, Bissell was employed in private practice from 1966-69 and 1972-78, first as an Associate and later as a Partner. He also acted as an Assistant United States Attorney in the District of New Jersey from 1969-71.
Bissell graduated from Phillips Exeter Academy in 1958 and went on to earn his B.A. from Princeton in 1962, followed by an L.L.B. from the University of Virginia School of Law in 1965. Subsequent to his retirement from the Court, he entered private practice at Connell Foley as Counsel, where he continues to serve both as Chair of the firm's Alternative Dispute Resolution Department and as a member of the Business Litigation practice group. Although Bissell considers his work in private practice to require expertise and skills distinct from those he honed as a federal judge, he has emphasized that his role as an adjudicator nonetheless provided for an efficient shift to his current function within arbitration and mediation processes. He has reflected particularly on the translatability of the skills of an adjudicator—hearing witnesses, reading evidence, drawing conclusion and explaining it in writing—to those of an arbitrator. The dynamic does shift vastly, however, between adjudicating, arbitrating, and mediating. Through arbitration and mediation, Bissell indicated that he has "polished a different set of techniques" from those sharpened through nearly twenty-five years on the bench.
The papers in this collection, representing decisions from the entirety of Bissell's tenure on the bench, provide significant insight into the workings of a busy urban federal court. Due to its inner-city setting in Newark, New Jersey, the Court decided a substantial number of cases involving antitrust and bank fraud issues, major drug prosecutions, and federal securities laws. Bissell's Court represents one of three federal trial courts in New Jersey, with the remaining two located in Trenton, the state's capital, and Camden. While the court's physical location may have impacted the types of cases adjudicated, as a federal judge Bissell ruled on cases in which the demography of vicinage was very diverse, encapsulating jurors, attorneys, and even parties to the actions from a wide range of urban, affluent suburban, and rural regions. Bissell noted that, while the courthouse was situated in a large-city locale, the district from which his cases arose stretched across the northern part of the state of New Jersey. As a result, jurors were pulled from city centers such as Newark and Jersey City, but also from many smaller rural towns along the Delaware River and out to Phillipsburg, as well as suburbs like Morristown in the very northern part of the state housing wealthy New York City-area commuters. Bissell reflected that his Court's jurors arrived from a relatively small geographic area, but an immensely varied demography. Similarly, Bissell's Court saw many attorneys from these representative areas, as well as those admitted pro hac vice from organizations and firms throughout the nation, appearing in the District of New Jersey on one-time bases for specific actions being tried. While attorneys hailed from a wide geographic distribution, the parties, too, originated from assorted locales, including those both national and international. In part, this range of parties was a result of their appearances within a federal trial court, as Bissell frequently heard diversity actions that otherwise would have been adjudicated within a state court. At the same time, however, the nature of the cases also led to the notable diversity of participants, as many of the commercial actions concerned business groups and companies throughout the United States and abroad.
Trends over time in the variety of cases contained within these papers likely are reflective of those nationally, displaying an increased number related to employment-law litigation, in particular employment-discrimination cases pertaining to race, age, and gender. Gradually more parties began to bring actions under Title VII of the 1964 Civil Rights Act and the 1967 Age Discrimination in Employment Act (ADEA), while the 1990 and 1993 passing of the Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA) and the Family and Medical Leave Act (FMLA), respectively, also led to increased employment-discrimination litigation. Bissell reflected that this trend also impacted some of his later decisions as he became more sensitive to individual conduct, the thwarting of equal protection, and other discriminatory practices affecting society. These cases range from race, age, and gender discrimination in police departments and government agencies to those arising from a variety of large and small private-business actions. The papers in this collection showcase an increased number of cases concerning rights-based litigation, in general. In addition to discriminatory employment practices, in the later years of Bissell's tenure, a large number of decisions concerning employment benefits were litigated, which is reflected in the numerous cases to which the Social Security Administration was a named party.
The decision of which Bissell is most proud concerns 21st-century race discrimination in the workplace. In this 2005 case, Lomack v. City of Newark, the former judge affirmed a lower court decision to integrate firehouse shifts in a Newark fire department, a place of employment that was widely segregated as a product of de facto segregation. Although his decision later was reversed by the Third Circuit Court of Appeals, Bissell noted of his contrary conclusion, "I feel very proud of this decision." At the same time, he noted how this case, in particular, reflects his own growing concern with civil rights issues in his later years on the bench. When asked whether he would have decided the same way if the case had come to him in 1983 instead of 2005, his "inkling was probably not."
While many of the cases in this collection remain unpublished, their significance for legal and historical research in future years is unmistakable. In addition to providing a historical record of general urban-court practices in the late 20th and early 21st centuries, Bissell hopes that these papers also will make clear the prevalence of judicial impartiality at the trial level and the significance of trial-court rulings generally, matters that frequently are not paid significant attention due to the academic and legal focus on appellate decisions and their inner-court workings. He has indicated that the social and political views of an individual judge should never hold a position in the adjudication process. The conscientious trial judge, Bissell noted, dedicates himself to deciding a case on its own merits both in terms of the facts involved and the law that applies; the role of a judge is not to ventilate or to inflict upon the parties involved a political, social, or sociological point of view. That has "no place there," Bissell indicated. He also reflected that his papers should produce for researchers both a sense of what it was like to be working as a federal trial court judge during this time span, along with the "products of a judge who, like almost all of them, calls them as he sees them without any baggage overlay." If his body of work helps to demonstrate these issues to both contemporary and future researchers, the now-retired judge indicated that he "would be very satisfied."
Scope and Content Information
The Papers of Judge John W. Bissell document his service on the U.S. District Court for the district of New Jersey from 1983-2005. The collection consists mainly of unpublished opinions, touching on a great diversity of topics, with a few published opinions and articles of correspondence selected for preservation by Judge Bissell.
The papers are divided by date into 2,377 files. Each file has been assigned a number of subject terms from a modified subset of the Library of Congress CRS Legislative Subject Terms Used in THOMAS (including the CRS Named-Entity Subject Terms Used in THOMAS). A full list of subject terms used in describing the Bissell papers appears on the Law Library web site. You may use the search box on the left to search the full finding aid for subject terms of interest.
Opinions in this collection which have been published or reported in LEXIS are noted by the phrase "Published as:" and the relevant citation.
Researchers should note that a few published opinions, issued by Judge Bissell during the time period represented by the papers donated to the University of Virginia Law Library Special Collections, nevertheless do not appear in this collection. A list of published opinions not represented in this collection is available on the Law Library web site.
Brief summaries have been written for many, though not all, of the cases in the years 1983-1988. The full list of summaries is available on the Law Library web site.
Organization
The papers are arranged alphabetically by case title within each calendar year. Note that some cases carry over across two or more years; they will be listed under the same case title in each year for which we have relevant documents.
A small number of undated papers have been filed at the back of Box 80.
Papers, 1983
Box: 1-2
Papers, 1984
Box: 2-4
Papers, 1985
Box: 4-6
Papers, 1986
Box: 6-9
Papers, 1987
Box: 9-13
Papers, 1988
Box: 13-17
Papers, 1989
Box: 17-21
Papers, 1990
Box: 21-26
Papers, 1991
Box: 26-31
Papers, 1992
Box: 31-35
Papers, 1993
Box: 36-38
Papers, 1994
Box: 38-42
Papers, 1995
Box: 43-46
Papers, 1996
Box: 47-50
Papers, 1997
Box: 51-54
Papers, 1998
Box: 55-59
Papers, 1999
Box: 59-63
Papers, 2000
Box: 64-67
Papers, 2001
Box: 68-70
Papers, 2002
Box: 71-73
Papers, 2003
Box: 74-76
Papers, 2004
Box: 77-78
Papers, 2005
Box: 79-80
Contents List
- Papers, 1983 (Box 1-2)
  All papers dated 1983.
  The papers are arranged alphabetically by case title within each calendar year. Note that some cases carry over across two or more years; they will be listed under the same case title in each year for which we have relevant documents.
  - Am. Home Prod. Corp. v. API Sys. 1983 April 08 (Box 1)
    Letter-Opinion; Stipulation and Order; Exhibits I, II, III; Decision (court transcript)
    Subject Terms
    Intellectual property
    Marketing and advertising
    Switzerland
    Medical tests and diagnostic methods
    General science and technology matters
    Summary available
  - Ashford v. United States 1983 May 20 (Box 1)
    Letter-Opinion
    Federal officials
    Jurisdiction and venue
  - Barlo Equip. Corp. v. Saddle River Tours 1983 March 18 (Box 1)
    Opinion; Order
    State and local courts
  - Bass River Assoc. v. Bass River Twp. 1983 September 16 (Box 1)
    Opinion; Order of Judgment; Appendices A & B
    Marine and inland water transportation
    Navigation, waterways, harbors
    Urban and suburban affairs and development
    Housing and Community Development
    State and local government operations
    Published as:
    Bass River Assoc. v. Bass River Twp., 573 F. Supp. 205 (D. N.J. 1983).
  - Blieden v. Florescue 1983 November 22 (Box 1)
    Banking and financial institutions regulation
    Financial services and investments
    Securities
  - Blue v. U.S. Bureau of Alcohol 1983 February 14 (Box 1)
    Letter-Opinion; Order
    Drug trafficking and controlled substances
    Criminal investigation, prosecution, interrogation
    Law enforcement officers
    Civil Rights and Liberties, Minority Issues
  - Cap Gemini Sogeti v. Applied Data Research, Inc. 1983 August 04 (Box 1)
    Letter; Order
    International monetary system and foreign exchange
  - Caravella v. Mayberry 1983 April 15 (Box 1)
    Mental health
    Veterans' medical care
  - Carpet Masters v. Carpet Masters 1983 November 29 (Box 1)
    Opinion; Order of Remand; Letter-Opinion
    Competition and antitrust
    Business ethics
    General business and commerce matters
    Small business
  - Clauso v. Studds 1983 September 28 (Box 1)
    Correctional facilities and imprisonment
    Members of Congress
    Religion
  - Davila v. Tard 1983 July 15 (Box 1)
    Detention of persons
  - Devine v. Handy 1983 June 14 (Box 1)
    Letter-Opinion; Order; Opinion (1983 June 21); Order
    Life, casualty, property insurance
    Contracts and agency
  - Diecidue v. Whitesmiths 1983 May 18 (Box 1)
    Judicial procedure and administration
  - Esposito v. Mintz 1983 April 12 (Box 1)
    Letter-Opinion; Letter-Opinion (1983 May 02); Order
    Postal service
    Lawyers and legal services
  - Fahey v. Carty 1983 May 20 (Box 1)
    Accidents
    Motor vehicles
    Legal fees and court costs
  - Feist & Feist Realty Corp. v. Hansford Prop. 1983 May 04 (Box 1)
    Federal appellate courts
    Judicial review and appeals
  - First State Underwriters Agency of New England Reinsurance Corp. v. Travelers Ins. Co. 1983 September 28 (Box 1)
    Letter-Opinion; Opinion of 3rd Cir. on appeal (1986 January 07)
  - Fitzgerald v. Cmty. Mem'l Hosp. 1983 May 04 (Box 1)
    Health care quality
  - Foca v. Econ. Lab. 1983 May 13 (Box 1)
    Opinion; Opinion (1983 September 01); Order
    Labor-management relations
    Alternative dispute resolution, mediation, arbitration
  - Gantt v. Western Union Tel. Co. 1983 January 26 (Box 1)
  - Gary v. Evans 1983 October 20 (Box 1)
    Letter-Opinion; Order of Dismissal; Amendment to Letter-Opinion (1983 October 25)
  - Gilmore v. State 1983 July 11 (Box 1)
  - Gluck v. United States 1983 December 19 (Box 1)
    Internal Revenue Service (IRS)
    General taxation matters
    Tax administration and collection, taxpayers
    Health information and medical records
  - Gordon v. Gordon 1983 March 02 (Box 1)
    Right of privacy
    Telephone and wireless communication
  - Hall v. Hicks 1983 June 27 (Box 1)
    Due process and equal protection
    Juvenile crime and gang violence
  - Hossic v. Mattingly 1983 March 02 (Box 1)
    Opinion
    Meat
  - Hotz v. Brown 1983 March 18 (Box 1)
  - Hough v. Bendix Corp. 1983 February 09 (Box 1)
    Opinion-Letter; Order
  - Hunt v. Mercer County Super. Ct. 1983 December 08 (Box 1)
    Letter-Opinion; Order of Dismissal; Opinion of 3rd Cir. for United States, ex rel. Rines v. Beister, et al. (1982 April 29)
    Criminal justice information and records
  - James v. N.J. State Parole Bd. 1983 February 02 (Box 1)
  - Johns-Manville Sales Corp. v. W. R. Grace & Co. 1983 November 15 (Box 1)
    Civil actions and liability
    Building construction
  - Kreuger Tech. v. Eco Recycling Serv. 1983 August 02 (Box 1)
    Letter-Opinion; Order of Remand
  - Lieberman v. Interstate Fire & Cas. Co. 1983 March 08 (Box 1)
    Opinion; Order; Affidavit
    Fires
  - McKinney v. Hercules 1983 June 20 (Box 1)
    Opinion (court transcript)
    Employee benefits and pensions
    Employee leave
    Employment discrimination and employee rights
    Disability and health-based discrimination
    Employment discrimination
    Sex, gender, sexual orientation discrimination
    Women's rights
    Sex and reproductive health
    Women's health
    Women's employment
  - Monmouth Cablevision Assoc. v. Hastings 1983 July 15 (Box 1)
    Judges
    Business investment and capital
  - Moody v. Tard 1983 July 08 (Box 1)
    Letter-Opinion; Order of Dismissal; Order
    Property rights
  - Morris v. Hilton 1983 February 24 (Box 1)
    Opinion; Order; Opinion (1983 June 02); Order
    Dental care
    Surgery and anesthesia
  - Muhammad v. Fauver 1983 February 10 (Box 1)
    Opinion-Letter; Order; Letter-Opinion (1983 April 13); Order; Opinion (1983 August 18); Order
  - Obi v. Mazza 1983 May 09 (Box 1)
    Racial and ethnic relations
  - Puchalski v. Tard 1983 April 04 (Box 1)
  - Raywood v. Mercer County Bd. of Freeholders 1983 March 24 (Box 1)
  - Regulski v. Gale 1983 May 31 (Box 2)
    Letter-Opinion; Order of Dismissal
  - Remington Rand Corp. v. Marine Midland Bank 1983 September 08 (Box 2)
  - Robert Morris Educ. Ass'n v. Bd. of Ed. of South Bound Brook 1983 December 15 (Box 2)
    Opinion; Order Granting Permanent Injunction; Judgment Granting Attorneys Fees and Court Costs
    School administration
    Elementary and secondary education
    Elections, voting, political campaign regulation
    Government employee pay, benefits, personnel management
  - Rob-E-Son v. E. D. Etnyre & Co. 1983 May 02 (Box 2)
    Air quality
  - Rodziewicz v. Feconda 1983 March 18 (Box 2)
  - Rountree v. Fenton 1983 March 29 (Box 2)
    Opinion; Order; Letter-Opinion (1983 August 09); Order
    Nutrition and diet
  - Sarullo v. Dumont 1983 October 20 (Box 2)
  - Sine v. Balogh 1983 May 19 (Box 2)
  - Sowa v. United States 1983 May 13 (Box 2)
    Opinion; Order for Declaratory Judgment Granting Jurisdiction
    Drug, alcohol, tobacco use
    Disability and paralysis
    Long-term, rehabilitative, and terminal care
    Military personnel and dependents
    Sowa v. United States, No. 82-2721, 1983 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 16999 (D. N.J. May 12, 1983).
  - Stanley v. White 1983 August 29 (Box 2)
  - Stolzenthaler v. Auto-Life Mgmt. 1983 May 04 (Box 2)
    Letter-Opinion; Order Dismissing the Complaint
    Administrative law and regulatory procedures
    Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC)
  - Thompson v. Dietz 1983 July 07 (Box 2)
  - Troche v. Vliet 1983 August 05 (Box 2)
    Letter-Opinion; Order; Opinion of 3rd Cir. for United States, ex rel. Rines v. Beister, et al. (1982 April 29)
    Criminal procedure and sentencing
  - Tucker v. Fauver 1983 March 10 (Box 2)
    Opinion; Order; Opinion (1983 December 02)
  - Tucker v. Von Roll 1983 June 06 (Box 2)
    Sports and recreation facilities
    Worker safety and health
  - Ukarish v. Magnesium Elektron 1983 March 01 (Box 2)
    Oral Opinion (court transcript)
    Assault and harassment offenses
    Industrial facilities
    Manufacturing
    Ukarish v. Magnesium Elektron, No. 81-638, 1983 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 18909 (D. N.J. Mar. 1, 1983).
  - United States v. Curran 1983 July 12 (Box 2)
    Government lending and loan guarantees
    Small Business Administration
    Credit and credit markets
  - United States v. One 1980 Chevrolet Corvette 1983 May 26 (Box 2)
    Opinion; Judgment
    Firearms and explosives
  - United States v. Raymond 1983 January 26 (Box 2)
    Letter-Opinion; Letter-Opinion (1983 January 31)
    Fraud offenses and financial crimes
    Military procurement, research, weapons development
  - United States v. Salconi 1983 November 04 (Box 2)
    Sentence (court transcript); Amended Order
    Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA)
    Puerto Rico
  - United States v. Tremarco 1983 February 24 (Box 2)
    Letter (untitled)
  - Walker v. Steig 1983 September 12 (Box 2)
    Ruling of the Court (court transcript)
  - Washington v. Hilton 1983 June 22 (Box 2)
  - Williams v. Tard 1983 September 28 (Box 2)
- Papers, 1984 (Box 2-4)
  All papers dated 1984.
  - Ahart v. Ocean County Prosecutor's Office 1984 April 17 (Box 2)
    Crimes against property
  - Arizona Telco Fed. Credit Union v. Cumis Ins. Soc'y 1984 September 04 (Box 2)
  - Bass River Assoc. v. Bass River Twp. 1984 January 24 (Box 2)
    Evidence and witnesses
  - Bimbo v. Hilton 1984 January 24 (Box 2)
  - Bullock v. Stiles 1984 June 05 (Box 2)
  - Burnett v. Monmouth County Bd. of Chosen Freeholders 1984 January 18 (Box 2)
  - Callaway v. Callaway 1984 June 19 (Box 2)
    U.S. Postal service
  - Chatman v. Pilgrim Life Ins. Co. 1984 November 02 (Box 2)
    Health care costs and insurance
    Cardiovascular and respiratory health
  - Clark v. N.J. Bell Local 827 1984 January 06 (Box 2)
    Opinion; Order; Order
  - Colon v. Brandt 1984 September 26 (Box 2)
    Infectious and parasitic diseases
  - Cometa Trading Co. v. Manuel Int'l 1984 November 30 (Box 2)
  - Conn. Gen. Life Ins. Co. v. E. Dental Ctr. of Ewing 1984 December 07 (Box 2)
  - Corsi v. Tard 1984 June 26 (Box 2)
    Letter-Opinion; Order; Order of Dismissal
  - Crane v. Fauver 1984 May 21 (Box 2)
  - Dick Carlisi Auto Body Corp. v. Steepy 1984 September 26 (Box 2)
    Opinion; Order for Summary Judgment; Letter from Sally Mrvos; Memorandum Opinion of the 3rd Cir. on appeal (1985 June 28)
    Public contracts and procurement
  - Donovan v. Opatut 1984 February 01 (Box 2)
    Real estate business
  - Evans v. Tard 1984 December 19 (Box 2)
  - Fell v. Kapsak 1984 April 04 (Box 2)
    Letter-Opinion; Dismissal Order; Order
  - Fitzpatrick v. I.V. DiMartino 1984 February 01 (Box 2)
  - Foy v. Fauver 1984 September 28 (Box 3)
  - Foy v. Tard 1984 September 20 (Box 3)
  - Gluck v. United States 1984 April 04 (Box 3)
    Letter-Opinion; Order; Letter from Sally Mrvos; Opinion of 3rd Cir. on appeal (1985 February 12)
  - Golin v. FMC Corp. 1984 February 01 (Box 3)
    Letter-Opinion; Order Permitting Supplementary Amendment to Original Complaint
  - Han v. Food and Nutrition Serv. 1984 March 08 (Box 3)
    Opinion; Order; Errata Order; Addendum Order
    Department of Agriculture
    Food assistance and relief
    Food industry and services
    Retail and wholesale trades
    Freedom of information
    Government investigations
  - Hinton v. Schroth 1984 June 25 (Box 3)
  - Hochman v. Zenith Radio Corp. 1984 July 03 (Box 3)
  - Holme v. United States 1984 November 28 (Box 3)
  - Irizarry v. Level Line, Inc. 1984 July 11 (Box 3)
    Motor carriers
    Transportation employees
  - Jackson v. Shibe 1984 September 04 (Box 3)
  - Kovack v. N.J. State Parole Bd. 1984 February 09 (Box 3)
  - La Torre v. Fauver 1984 July 13 (Box 3)
    Opinion; Order; Order of Dismissal
  - La Torre v. Zelinski 1984 July 13 (Box 3)
  - Laborers' Local Union Nos. 472 & 172 v. Agabiti Bros. 1984 January 24 (Box 3)
    Letter-Opinion; Order Confirming Arbitration Award
  - Laufgas v. Janes 1984 November 13 (Box 3)
    Letter-Opinion; Order; Order; Order
  - Lieberman v. Interstate Fire & Cas. Co. 1984 November 02 (Box 3)
    Tax-exempt organizations
  - Luiz v. Heckler 1984 October 25 (Box 3)
    Opinion; Order of Remand
    Department of Health and Human Services
    Hereditary and development disorders
    Disability assistance
  - Macon v. Twp. of Old Bridge 1984 February 29 (Box 3)
    Political movements and philosophies
    Protest and dissent
  - Martin v. Heckler 1984 October 11 (Box 3)
    Social security and elderly assistance
  - McClintock v. Griffith 1984 April 17 (Box 3)
    Administrative remedies
  - McClintock v. Somerset County Prosecutor's Office 1984 April 19 (Box 3)
    Government liability
  - Miller v. Tard 1984 September 20 (Box 3)
    Opinion; Order for Summary Judgment
    First Amendment rights
  - Monmouth Cablevision Assoc. v. Hastings 1984 September 20 (Box 3)
    Television and film
    Corporate finance and management
  - Moon v. Ross 1984 December 04 (Box 3)
    Letter-Opinion; Order Dismissing Plaintiff's Complaint